Hello and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan, and today
we're going to be learning about
the strength of acids and bases.
And the whole idea here is that acids and
bases, they dissociate when dissolved,
when they're added to aqueous solutions.
Now whenever you have acids and bases,
the reason they dissolve is that they
are considered to be electrolytes.
Now the thing with electrolytes is
that there's two major definitions.
There are strong electrolytes,
and there's also weak.
Now, strong electrolytes, the most
important thing about them is that
when they dissociate, they dissociate
completely, meaning that whenever, what
we mean when we say that is that when
you throw, let's say, HA into solution.
It's going to be making all hydrogen ions
and a minus ions when that's thrown into
solution all Ions when we are here, right?
There's gonna be no more remnants of the
major molecule When that's thrown in and
the same thing applies to basis to write
if you throw a strong base Let's say like
hodges like sodium hydroxide You will get
B plus and then all OH minus in solution.
They completely dissociate.
Now with weak, they partially dissociate.
They're still considered acids and bases.
They still conduct electricity.
However, it is a very, it's a
lot less because you don't have
as many positive and negative
cations and anions in solution.
There's a lot less.
So when it comes to the solution,
so up above, I use a, I use a giant
arrow to show complete dissociation.
up here, even though we still will
write that it makes H plus and a
minus as it dissociates, there's
not going to be as many solution.
So you'll notice is that there's
a bunch of H a molecules that
are still connected together.
Notice how there's no charge on them.
They're just in their molecular form.
And then you'll have a
few ions in solution.
So you still write the same dissociation.
But, there's not going to
be as many in terms of the
concentration of ions in solution.
Now, with this, we essentially as
chemists, we use what we refer to as an
equilibrium constant, which is called
the acid dissociation constant, to
tell you how strong or how weak it is.
This is the same thing as a K value,
but instead the only difference is that
we put a little A next to it to tell
you, hey, we're referring to acids.
So there's an acid dissociation
constant, and then there's also a base
dissociation constant, which is a KB.
We typically only really use Ka
though, 99 percent of the time.
So when it comes to Ka's, the
whole idea here is that they
determine the strength of the acid.
Okay.
So the bigger the value there is, the
more products, the weak, the smaller
the value there is, the more reactants.
So the more H plus ions that are
made, the more electricity that you'll
have, the stronger it's going to be.
So using this whole products over
reactants idea, so drill that saying
in your head, products over reactants,
because when it comes to equilibrium,
we're going to be saying that quite
frequently when we're trying to write.
These different equations.
So when it comes to them being strong,
whether it's a strong acid or a
strong electrolyte, typically that
Ka is much greater than one because
there are a whole ton of ions, right?
All products in there.
So this number is really, really big.
And as a result, this number is as tiny as
it can get because you have all products.
Meaning, it's kind of like saying,
what is, uh, 10, 000, uh, 10, 000
ions compared to one molecule, right?
So it's like a 10, 000 to one.
That's huge, right?
As a difference.
Whereas when you have like a weak acid,
well, it's going to be like the opposite.
It's kind of like saying, Hey, we
have one mallet, we have one ion in
solution and 10, 000 molecules there.
So what's one divided by 10, 000, it's
going to be a really small decimal value.
It's all about the ratios of
how we are looking at these.
Let's go look at some
different examples of this.
So when we are writing these, the first
thing we gotta do is understand and
be able to write reversible arrows,
because they allow us to be able
to represent weak acids and bases.
So let's say if I have an acid
and a base here, so I have HA,
which is our acid, and water, in
this case, is going to be a base.
So that means that HA is going
to donate its proton to water,
so we'll write that out.
And as a result, we're going to have A
minus and then H3O plus for hydronium.
Now when we are writing this, there's
a couple notes that need to be made, is
we're going to write our Ka equation.
When we are writing them, we
never include, never include
solids or pure liquids like water.
The reason we don't include
them is that their concentration
is considered to be constant.
In terms of water, there's so
much water in solution that it,
your values won't make any sense
because they don't represent the
actual chemistry that's occurring.
They, we only are curious about the
solute or the very tiny piece of it.
So if we were to write this Ka equation.
The next thing that we got to do
is do products over reactants,
but how do we show them?
Well, we use brackets to indicate
molarity when we are writing these.
So every product and every reactants can
be surrounded by square brackets, which
will indicate how much molarity there is.
Um, so let's do that.
So if we have, let's say a minus,
so we'll put that in brackets.
So products, a minus.
and H3O so from our formula on the top,
and that's all going to be divided by the
reactants, so products over reactants.
We don't include water, so we're
just going to write A minus,
H3O all over HA in brackets.
Now the reason we only include
these other ones is because
they are all aqueous, right?
So every one of these is aqueous,
And then water is considered to be a
liquid, so we don't write that one.
So now the thing about this, if
you calculate this, so if we had
all the concentrations, we had
them all measured, you usually
would get a Ka that's very small.
You might get one that's 10 to the
negative 1 to 10 to the negative 14.
It's usually very, very small
when you're talking about weak
acids and using Ka values.
Now, the thing about these though,
the strength and molarity of an
acid determine the acid's Ka.
Okay, so depending on how strong of an
acid it is and what the concentration.
Now the thing to keep in mind, an
acid can be considered strong, meaning
HCl, sulfuric acid, nitric acid, but
it can have a diluted concentration.
So don't just think like, oh, when
we say something is strong, It
means that it's like very powerful.
It could be, you know,
very little molarity.
And the other thing about it is that
you can also have a weak acid that
is a, has a very, very high molarity.
So they're not relevant to each other.
Molarity and the strength
is what I'm trying to say.
Let's look at some examples of this.
All right, so our first one here,
looking at acid base equilibrium.
The first thing is we got
to write out our reaction.
So we have HCl reacting with water.
HCl is a strong acid, so it's going
to be donating its proton to water.
And as a result, what are
we going to be making?
Well, we will have Cl minus as one
product, then the other one is going to be
H3O plus that we're going to make as well.
Now when we are trying to write
out the, uh, Ka factor, being that
we were, I gave a value for Ka.
So with this one, it's a strong acid,
so notice that it's a very big number.
1.
3 times 10 to the 6th power, right?
That's telling you you
have six zeros behind this.
So it's over a million is how big this is.
It's very large.
So what we will do is we'd write 1.
3 times 10 to the 6th and equal
that two products over reactants.
So what we'll do is we'll
use spur square brackets.
We have chlorine ion.
Then H3O plus ion and then all that's
going to be over HCl and we exclude
water because water is considered
the solvent and is a pure substance.
So then that's how you would write that.
Now the other thing here we
have down below is HF in water.
Now, the one thing to kind of
point out about these two different
reactions is notice the arrows
and their difference here, right?
The HCl plus water has a single
arrow, hydrofluoric acid or
HF has a reversible arrow.
So we use reversible to denote whenever
it's weak in a weak acid or base.
And we use a single arrow to say,
Hey, we have a strong acid or base.
So it's one way to be able to see
the difference when you see it.
So with this one, HF is the acid.
So it donates its proton.
So what we're gonna have is
F minus leftover, and then H
three oh plus as your other ion.
If we were to write out the KA.
So we'd have Ka is equal to F minus, in
brackets, times H3O plus, in brackets,
all over the concentration of HF.
And that's how you'd write
out an equilibrium constant.
And the thing that's important
here is it tells you that being
that this is A lot less than one
is that it favors the reactants.
So most of this, of the population
of the solution is going to
be on the left hand side.
Whereas when we were looking at the
right one, that one was greater than one.
So most of that is going to be on the
right hand side of the, of the equation.
Let's go look at some more.
Dye and triprotic acids also exist.
Now these are generally weak acids
that have multiple hydrogens.
So one example is carbonic
acid, which is a diprotic acid,
meaning two protons, diprotic.
So if you have those two
hydrogens, they will dissociate.
However, when it comes to acids,
you don't rip them all off at once.
They lose one at a time, right?
So acids lose one proton at a time.
That is very important to
realize, is one at a time.
So here I have H2CO3.
yields H plus and HCO3 minus
when you throw it into water.
So how would we write this
in terms of the Ka value?
So being that it has multiple
protons, you'll kind of notice on
the right hand or the left hand
side here is that there's a Ka1.
So it's telling you the
first proton comes off.
So the way that we would say this
is we have Ka1 and we put H plus in
brackets, HCO3 minus in brackets.
And then the H2CO3 on the bottom.
So this would be the first one.
Now, being that this has multiple protons,
The thing about it is that, well, the
reaction could keep going, actually.
You can actually write more.
So we can actually take, let's say
if we had a second Ka value, we can
bring that up here, and we can actually
say, oh, well, what would happen
if I took, let's say, HCO3 minus,
and I wanted to further dissociate
this, how would this actually work?
Well, it would make, essentially, H plus.
And then co minus would be
the other ingredient as this
dissociated even further.
And then we could write Ako.
Essentially another Ka value for
the next portion and notice that
the charges change too, right?
We have a minus and then a two
minus on the next part, right?
It slowly loses more and more and we have
a different Ka value for the next part.
Notice how the value is a lot smaller
telling you that this isn't as common.
There's very little of these products
actually existing in solution.
This is so carbonic acid.
So the neat part about it is
this is actually the chemical.
It helps maintain the pH of your blood.
So this is what establishes itself to
make sure that your pH does not change
by very much when you essentially eat
anything or drink anything or anything
like that gets in contact with your
body that has no harmful effects.
Let's take a look at some more examples.
The autoionization of water means that
water can automatically ionize itself
when it's in a solution of itself.
So water can act as either an acid
or a base, which is one of the
most unique characteristics of it.
It allows it to do all kinds
of chemistry as a result.
Now, being that it can be either,
uh, so anytime you have a substance
that can do both, this is referred
to as amphoteric, meaning it
can do either an acid or a base.
So if I have, let's say two water
molecules and they want to react
with each other, which one's
the acid, which one's the base?
Well, we can choose, right?
It doesn't have to necessarily
be one or the other.
So let's say the one on the
left is the acid, and then the
one on the right is the base.
So what exactly are you
going to make as a result?
Well, if we donate our proton to the
other one, we are going to pretty
much have on the left hand side,
what's left is OH minus, and then
we'll also have H plus as a result,
which if you kind of remember, that is
your Arrhenius acid base definition.
Water produces protons,
and it produces hydroxides.
It also follows the Bronsted
Lowry definition, right?
It donated a proton, it
received a proton, it fits both.
So they can do that.
So whenever we are looking at some
of these different chemicals, right?
Can we see that, well, when we
have a water, can we have where
one water molecule donates its
proton to the other side and
gives away its proton as a result.
Alright, so with that being
donated, we have essentially a
really, really happy water who
has an extra positivity behind it.
And then a very sad water who
lost its poor little proton.
So whenever we have an H plus release
by an acid, water will pick it up.
Okay.
So one thing about this, that's
really important to realize is
that H plus is generally written to
talk about how acidic something is.
We can also use hydronium
ion to represent that too.
So H3O plus, So those two are
generally considered to be equivalent
to one another in solution.
So there's two ways, two different
ways to look at this, right?
Acids can dissociate to make H plus, or
we can also say that acids increase how
much H3O plus there are in solution.
Both tell you that the pH of these
different solutions is going to
essentially be going lower and lower
and lower, or more acidic as a result.
because of this increase
in hydrogen concentration.
So they both are equivalent
to each other, which is really
important to write down and note.
All right, let's take a
look at the next part.
Other examples are of polyprotic ions.
Other examples of amphoteric
molecules are polyprotic ions.
So something like HCO3 minus can
behave like both an acid and a base.
So one, so meaning that it either
can donate a hydrogen or receive one.
So for example, if I were to
draw on both sides, the different
types of how can this molecule go?
If I have an additional proton,
we will have carbonic acid, right?
So H2CO3.
And on the other way, if I lose a proton.
I will have CO3 2 minus.
So with this particular molecule,
it could either receive one
or it could donate one away.
So when it comes to acid bases, it
depends on how you look at it, right?
If it went this way,
essentially it is receiving one.
So it's actually acting like a base.
If it goes the other way to the
right, it's acting like an acid.
So, it's all about what direction
do we actually see it going when
it comes to being an acid or a
base or accepting or donating.
Let's look at the next part.
Now the most important part, what
comes with the autoionization of
water, is all about that relationship.
It is a Bronsted Lowry acid and base.
It's also an Arrhenius acid and base.
So when it comes to writing the
K factor for this, one thing
we can actually do for this.
Is we can write that K factor
as essentially H plus times OH
minus and we exclude the waters.
Now why is that so important?
Is it tells you we have an inverse
relationship, meaning that as H
plus goes up, OH minus goes down and
the opposites occur as well, right?
As the, as the acidity goes down.
The more alkaline or basic it is goes up.
So one thing that we can actually do here
is that there is a relationship here at
room temperature for, for this constant.
So we call it a KW constant.
So it's all about water dissociation.
And what we have here is
H plus times OH minus.
Those two concentrations
multiplied by each other.
equals 1.
0 times 10 to the negative 14.
So now why is that so big is that no
matter what concentration in solution
you have of H plus or hydrogen ion
or protons and hydroxide ions, if
you multiply those two concentrations
together, You're always going to get 1.
0 times 10 to the negative 14.
So this is a really very important
fact, a formula to realize of what
the scale is of acidity when it
comes to room temperature solutions.
And one thing you might realize
is that, okay, I have that 14
number all the way at the top.
Well, one thing to think about is
what's the size of the pH scale.
And you might remember or you're going
to learn about is that the pH scales goes
from generally about zero to fourteen.
So what this number is going to lead
to is what your pH scale is, which
is an easier way to be able to see
how acidic or basic something is
rather than looking at molarities
and concentrations all the time.
Let's keep moving.
So the next part, realizing
that's to do with solutions.
Let's talk about neutrality.
Well, if you have a neutral solution, this
is referred to as a pH of seven, right?
So it's right in the
middle of your pH scale.
How did they get that value?
Where does it come from?
So when, let's say if I had the following
value, where if you have a neutral
solution, that means the acidity is equal
to how basic or alkaline the solution is.
So meaning H plus is equal to hydroxide.
If they're equal, let's do some simple
math to kind of think about that.
How does that work?
Well, if they're the same, let's
just use a variable to describe that.
So let's say that I have H plus here
and OH minus, and let's just say that
they're equal to, let's just say X
being that we're used to algebra.
We've used X probably most of your lives.
So if we say, Hey, we have X.
times x and that's equal to 1.
0 times 10 to the negative 14.
What's the first thing you can do?
Let's do x times x.
What do you get?
Well, you'd have squared.
So now if I have x squared and I have 1.
0 times 10 negative 14,
how do you get x by itself?
How do you cancel out the square?
Well, the thing you can do is
we can square root it, right?
We can square root both sides.
So if that's to happen, right, these
cancel out and what you are going
to get is that x is equal to 1.
0 times 10 to the negative.
Now why is that so important
is if you think of neutrality.
So with the seven value.
One, one of the most important factors
is that if you have a pH equal to
seven, that's considered to be neutral.
So let's try to see of what implications
this means in terms of determining
if something's acidic or basic.
When we have something that's considered
to be neutral, that is when the
hydrogen concentration or the protons.
are equal to the hydroxide
concentration or OH minus.
So when these are equal, the
concentration of each of them is
going to be 10 to the negative seventh
power, and that's going to be molarity.
So that's a pH seven.
Now, when something is acidic, that means
you have way more protons in solution.
So we're going to increase that
number and also decrease hydroxide.
Remember, there's a
relationship as one goes up.
The other goes down.
So that means that you're going to
have a bigger number for 10 to the
minus 10 to the minus seven, like 10
to the minus five, four, three, two.
So it's getting larger that number, right?
It's going to be like 0.
001 0.
01, much bigger when it's basic.
That means that that number
is going to be a lot smaller.
So anywhere from like 10 to
the negative eight to 10 to
the negative 14, for example.
So if we were to try to do this
as an example, and I asked you,
what kind of solution do we have?
If you have 1.
0 times 10 to the negative 4 as your
concentration, is that bigger or smaller?
Now, for a lot of students, it's
usually really hard to try to understand
and interpret scientific notation.
So for this one, if you were to really
think about it, well, how many times
am I really moving that decimal place?
Well, it's going to be 0, 0, 0, 1.
Now, is that bigger or
greater than neutral?
Well, neutral is negative seven.
So we have one, two, three,
four, five, six, seven.
Which one is larger?
And you can kind of see, you can see
really quickly that the one on the
left, which is our original number is
a lot bigger than the other one, right?
It's sometimes that's that, that
power is misleading when you see that.
So what that tells you is
that this is very acidic.
Now if I asked you a follow up
question, how do you figure out
what the hydroxide concentration is?
Well, if you had to do that, we could
rearrange that equation up there
and we can essentially say that,
all right, well, I have O H minus.
I'll divide the H plus from
the other side, so we have 1.
0 times 10 to the negative 14, divide
that by the H plus concentration, and
we can figure out what the OH minus is.
So let's plug in our number.
What would we get?
So as a result, we would have 1.
0 times 10 to the
negative 14, divided by 1.
0 times 10 to the negative 4.
And you'd quickly find out that
that is going to be about 1.
0 times 10 to the negative 10
molarity when it comes to the
concentration of OH minus.
So notice that it's a
lot smaller of a value.
It's 10 power.
So it should be over inverse relationship.
And this is how you can try to
solve this particular problem.
So let's go to our final summary.
When it comes to trying to
understand the strengths of acids
and bases, it fully depends on the
level of chemistry you're taking.
If you're taking just introductory
chemistry, which is just for the beat for
beginners in chemistry I would recommend
really memorizing your strong acids and
bases It's a very good starting point
to go same thing if you're in general
chemistry one as well There are seven
strong acids and then we also have the
strong bases, which is all of the soluble
hydroxide salts Which are mainly the
alkali metals Um, so all the alkali metals
and then essentially the first three
alkaline metals on your periodic table.
So if you remember those, you
generally will be fine knowing
the majority of chemicals.
If you don't see one of
these, that means it's weak.
About 98 percent of acids and bases
or more are weak acids and bases.
But if you know these seven, it will
save you a lot of time and frustration.
So strength is all about looking at
the equilibrium values, which we'll
look in more detail in future videos.
But this is an idea of the basic idea
of how to set this up and understand
where the pH scale comes from is all
about how strong an acid or base is.
And that's what we'll look
into in our next video.
So thank you so much for listening.
I hope that this video helped you.
If you are confused, reach
out to me and ask for help.
Um, if you are not, if you're not one
of my students and you still want to
help and learn more, comment below
and let me know what you thought.
Um, and if this is your first time
here, please hit that like and subscribe
button and let me know if you ever need
anything at all for your chemistry needs.
If you want a particular video,
let me know and I'll see what if
I can help you and try to make
a, make future content for you.
Alright, thank you so much and
I hope you have a wonderful
day and I'll see you all later.
Bye now.